Guide to the John Seelye Papers, 1862-2015 and undated RL.11381
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research/Subject files, 1945-2014; undated; 3
  - Tramp: Chicago Daily News, 1964 (Box 9)
  - Tramp: Photographs, 1963 (Box 30)
  - TV file clippings, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Twain biblio: T Sawyer, undated (Box 9)
  - Unidentified maps, undated (Box 31)
  - Vermont Academy, undated (Box 9)
  - Voodoo, 2005 (Box 28)
  - for Webster book, undated (Box 9)
  - West of Everything interview, National Humanities Center "Soundings", undated (Box 29, Audio-cassette RL11381-CS-004)
    Jane Tompkins interview at National Humanities Center. Recording on Side B.
  - Wild Man corres, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
  - Wild Man in Walden MLA, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Wild Man notes, undated (Box 9)
  - Wild Man notes, undated (Box 9)
  - Wild Man outline, undated (Box 9)
  - Wister, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Wonderful O, 1988; undated (Box 9)
  - Wyman, Seth, 1962; undated (Box 9)
- Writings, 1862; 1950s-2000s; 4
  Seelye's writings have been sorted into subseries based on format: Reviews, Poetry, Articles and Prose, Books, and Edited Works. The Writings series contains drafts, proofs, edits, published works, and related correspondence and research collected by Seelye.
  - Reviews, 1950s-2000s; 4
    The Reviews subseries includes Seelye's regular columns reviewing popular literature, as well as assorted scholarly reviews in journals. This subseries includes specific articles arranged alphabetically by the author of the work being reviewed, as well as batches of publications containing regular contributions by Seelye. Authors reviewed by Seelye include Ray Bradbury, Stephen King, James Baldwin, Studs Terkel, Sacvan Bercovitch, and Dow Mossman; frequent subjects of works include American literature, American environment, the American West, and specific authors such as Walt Whitman, Herman Melville, and Mark Twain. Includes Seelye's 1972 review of Dow Mossman's The Stones of Summer and subsequent press and copies of the documentary, The Stone Reader, produced in 2002-2003.
    - A-T, 1950s-2000s; 130 folders (Box 10)
    - A-T, 1968-1992 (Box 28)
    - V-Z, 1970s-1980s; 14 folders (Box 11)
      Individually foldered reviews by Seelye, arranged by author of the work.
    - The Stones of Summer, 1972; 2003; 2 volumes (Box 26)
      Original and republished books by Dow Mossman.
    - Stone Reader, 2003; 3 dvds (Box 26, Dvd RL-11381-DVD-001, 002, 003)
      Limited Edition film by Mark Moskowitz
    - Stone Reader, 2001; 2 VHS (Box 26, Video-cassette RL-11381-VHS-001, 002)
      Rough cuts of Stone Reader, parts 1-5
    - Book World (Washington Post), 1970s (Box 12)
    - Book World (Washington Post), 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - Chicago Magazine, 1982-1991 (Box 12)
    - Chicago Magazine, 1980-1982; 6 folders (Box 28)
    - Chicago Tribune, 1982-1985 (Box 28)
    - Film Quarterly, 1964-1966 (Box 12)
    - Harpers, 1975 (Box 28)
    - The New Republic, 1970s; 5 folders (Box 12)
    - New York Times Book Reviews, 1972-1973 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - New York Times Book Reviews, 1985 (Box 31)
    - Nineteenth-Century Literature, 1980s-1990s (Box 12)
    - Philadelphia Inquirer, 1983-1984 (Box 12)
    - Philadelphia Inquirer, 1983-1985 (Box 28)
    - Saturday Review, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Times Literary Supplement, 1986 (Box 28)
    - The Virginia Quarterly, 1960s-1980s; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Poetry, 1965-2005; undated; 5
    Manuscript drafts and published poems by Seelye, largely unsorted and untitled.
    - Assorted poetry drafts, 1970s-1990s; 11 folders (Box 11)
      Excerpts, drafts, and sketches of poems, many untitled
    - BOEMB, 1965 (Box 30)
    - Something Happened, undated (Box 11)
    - John Junior, undated (Box 11)
    - Barnes poem, 2005 (Box 11)
    - Humor, undated (Box 11)
    - Six Poems, 2006 (Box 11)
    - Inquest, 1972 (Box 11)
    - Garbage, 1972 (Box 11)
    - Vermont Academy Centennial poem, undated (Box 29)
  - Articles and Prose, 1950s-2000s; 6
    Drafts, edits, and published versions of Seelye's short stories, fiction essays, academic articles, and scholarly works; includes both complete (unpublished and published) works as well as many unfinished pieces. This series has been arranged by title of the work.
    - A-E, 1950s-2000s; 80 folders (Box 13)
      Drafts, notes, typed copies, and published versions of Seelye's prose and scholarly articles. Arranged alphabetically by title. Includes prospectus for Alpheus; his Berkeley Gazette Daily columns; Black on White; preparatory materials for Border; columns for the Wesleyan Cardinal; and numerous unpublished articles and story drafts.
    - A-E, 1950s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 29)
    - E-L, 1950s-2000s; 60 folders (Box 14)
      Drafts, notes, typed copies, and published versions of Seelye's prose and scholarly articles. Arranged alphabetically by title. Includes drafts of Huckleberry Finn, Herman Melville, and Horatio Alger scholarship; several versions of "Holden in the Museum" essay; an article about Fahrenheit 451; and a "Juvenalia" file with collected drafts and poems from Seelye's youth and college years.
    - E-L, 1950s-2000s (Box 29)
    - L-S, 1950s-2000s; 80 folders (Box 15)
      Drafts, notes, typed copies, and published versions of Seelye's prose and scholarly articles. Arranged alphabetically by title. Includes several versions of "Moby King," "Retro Fiction," and "The Return;" also notes about Robert MacNish.
    - L-S, 1950s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 29)
    - S-Z, 1950s-2000s; 49 folders (Box 16)
      Drafts, notes, typed copies, and published versions of Seelye's prose and scholarly articles. Arranged alphabetically by title. Includes several folders of Seelye's short prose, short essays, and unsorted drafts, some fiction and some academic; several versions of The Tramp; and the prospectus and publisher notes for Throwaway.
    - S-Z, 1950s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 29)
    - "The Writer," in Frederic Remington: The Masterworks, 1988 (Box 26)
      Published catalog from Saint Louis Art Museum
    - "Some green thoughts on a green theme," in Literature in Revolution, 1972 (Box 26)
      Northwestern University Press, 1972.
    - "Some green thoughts on a green theme," in Literature in Revolution, 1972 (Box 29)
      serial and paperback versions
    - Times Literary Supplement, no. 11, 1972 (Box 26)
  - Books written by Seelye, 1950s-2004; 7
    The books subseries contains material documenting monographs written by Seelye, both fiction and scholarly works. Files contain drafts, edits, proofs, images and illustrations, and publisher correspondence; some titles have numerous draft versions while others contain only the published volume. Published volumes are held in Box 25 and 26.
    - The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn: A Revised and Corrected Edition, undated; 2 folders (Box 17)
      Edited typescript draft
    - A Bad Start, undated; 2 folders (Box 17)
      Typescript draft
    - Beautiful Machine: Rivers and the Republican Plan 1755-1825, 1991 (Box 25)
      New York: Oxford University Press, 1991.
    - Booger Potts, undated (Box 17)
    - Bret Harte / Joaquin Miller Border Drama book (untitled), 1970s; 7 folders (Box 17)
      Typescript draft, source materials, research materials, and reference/notes by Seelye
    - Careless Love: My Days and Nights with Sylvia Plath (A Memoir Mostly), undated (Box 17)
    - Come to the Wildwood, undated; 7 folders (Box 17)
      Typescript drafts, edited typescript drafts, research articles and notes. Includes drafts of alternate titles: Balaam and Come, Come to the Wildwood.
    - Dark Wonders, undated; 8 folders (Box 18)
      Typescript drafts, edited typescript drafts
    - Dirty Tricks, or Nick Noxin's Natural Nobility, 1973 (Box 18)
      Uncorrected advance proofs
    - Dirty Tricks, or Nick Noxin's Natural Nobility, 1973 (Box 25)
      New York: Liveright, 1973.
    - For Fear of Little Men, undated (Box 18)
      Typescript fragments, incomplete
    - Granite Dan, 1997; undated; 3 folders (Box 18)
      Typescript drafts, with edits; graphics; other research and notes
    - Jane Eyre's American Daughters, 2002-2004 (Box 18)
      Publisher's correspondence, revisions
    - Jane Eyre's American Daughters: From The Wide, Wide World to Anne of Green Gables, A Study of Marginalized Maidens and What They Mean, 2005 (Box 25)
      Newark: University of Delaware Press, 2005.
    - The Kid, 1972; undated; 9 folders (Box 18)
      Typescript drafts, unrevised proof, chapter drafts, notes and questions
    - The Kid, 1971-1974; 6 volumes (Box 25)
      New York: Viking Press, 1972. London: Chatto and Windus, 1972. London: Coronet Books, 1974. Unrevised proof (Viking Press), 1971. New York: Dell Printing, 1973. London: Odhams, 1974.
    - Lines of Thought: Triangulations in American Art, undated; 23 folders (Box 19)
      Typescript drafts, revised drafts, graphics, images, notes from presentations, etc. Includes alternate titles: Delta Destinies, Early Comers.
    - Luck, undated; 4 folders (Box 19)
      Typescript drafts, including correspondence and edits
    - Mark Twain in the Movies, undated; 4 folders (Box 19)
      Typescript drafts and edits
    - Mark Twain in the Movies, 1977 (Box 25)
      New York: The Viking Press, 1977.
    - Melville: The Ironic Diagram, 1970 (Box 25)
      Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1970. 2 versions.
    - Melville's Ironic Mode: Dissertation, undated; 5 folders (Box 20)
      Typescript draft, notes, and edits
    - Melville's Ironical Way: Master's thesis, undated; 3 folders (Box 20)
      Typescript
    - Memory's Nation: The Place of Plymouth Rock, undated; 26 folders (Box 20-21)
      Typescript drafts, including early and "final" versions; edited page proofs; illustrations, graphics
    - Memory's Nation: The Place of Plymouth Rock, 1998 (Box 25)
      Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, 1998.
    - The Pilgrim, 1953 (Box 22)
      Published by The Art Laboratory, Wesleyan University
    - The Plains of Kansas, 1972-1973; undated; 17 folders (Box 22)
      Typescript drafts, some unsorted pages, and publisher correspondence
    - The Plains of Kansas, undated; 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Prophetic Waters: The River in Early American Life and Literature, 1977 (Box 25)
    - A Puzzle Piece, undated; 2 folders (Box 22)
      Typescript drafts
    - Seidi's Excellent Wildwood Adventure, undated; 8 folders (Box 22)
      Typescript drafts, some incomplete and some with edits
    - Seidi II: What Happened Next..., undated; 2 folders (Box 23)
      Typescript draft, incomplete with edits
    - Sparrow: A Romance, undated; 4 folders (Box 23)
      Typescript drafts, including edits
    - Stolen Sweets, undated; 12 folders (Box 23)
      Typescript drafts, including comments by Doris Betts; edits; chronology and charater notes; incomplete chapter drafts
    - The Structure and Meaning of Herman Melville's Later Fiction Related to his Ontological Viewpoint, 1956 (Box 23)
      Master's thesis
    - The True Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, 1970; 2 volumes (Box 25)
    - Un Saque d'Histoires Petites Marveleuse..., 2000 (Box 23)
    - War Games, 2001-2007; 5 folders (Box 24)
      Publisher correspondence, essay "War and the Novel", and artwork
    - War Games, 2003; 2 volumes (Box 25)
      University of Massachusetts Press, 2003. 2 versions.
    - What was that sound? A terrifying mystery story!, 2002; undated; 5 folders (Box 24)
  - Books edited by Seelye, 1862-2007; 8
    This subseries documents Seelye's work as an editor and scholar, and includes works that he edited for Penguin and other publishers, as well as works where he contributed introductions, forewords, afterwords, or footnotes. Published volumes are held in Box 25 and 26.
    Of note is the original 1862 edition of Life of Asa Sheldon, Wilmington Farmer, which Seelye edited and republished as Yankee Drover in 1988.
    - Alger, Horatio: Digging for Gold, undated (Box 11)
      Introduction, proof. Edited by Seelye.
    - Alger, Horatio: The Young Miner; Or, Tom Nelson in California, 1965 (Box 25)
      Book Club of California. Introduction and Bibliographical Note by Seelye.
    - Arthur Gordon Pym, Benito Cereno, and Related Writings: Works by Edgar Allan Poe and Herman Melville, 1967 (Box 26)
      J. B. Lippencourt. Edited by Seelye.
    - Browne, J. Ross: Etchings of a Whaling Cruise, 1968 (Box 26)
      Cambridge: Belknap Press. Edited by Seelye.
    - Burroughs, Edgar Rice: A Princess of Mars, undated (Box 11)
      Edited draft of introduction.
    - Burroughs, Edgar Rice: A Princess of Mars, 1990 (Box 25)
      Penguin Classics. Introduction by Seelye.
    - Burroughs, Edgar Rice: A Princess of Mars, 2007 (Box 25)
    - Burroughs, Edgar Rice: Tarzan of the Apes, 1990 (Box 29)
      Penguin Classics. Introduction by Seelye
    - Dana, Richard Henry: Two Years Before the Mast, 2000 (Box 26)
      Signet Classic. Introduction by Seelye.
    - Kaler, James Otis: Toby Tyler, 1976 (Box 11)
      Draft of introduction by Seelye.
    - Kipling, Rudyard: Captains Courageous, 2005 (Box 25)
    - London, Jack: White Fang and The Call of the Wild, 1991 (Box 25)
    - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth: Evangeline, undated (Box 11)
      Drafts by Seelye for introduction or essay.
    - Marryat, Frederick: Masterman Ready, 1975 (Box 11)
      Publisher correspondence, draft, and proofs of preface by Seelye.
    - Melville, Herman: The Confidence-Man:His Masquerade, 1968 (Box 29)
      Chandler Facsimile Edition. Introduction, illustrations, and bibliography by Seelye
    - Smith, Richard Penn: On to the Alamo: Colonel Crockett's Exploits and Adventures in Texas, 2003 (Box 25)
    - Steinbeck, John: The Red Pony, 1994 (Box 26)
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis: Kidnapped, 2000 (Box 25)
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis: Treasure Island, 1999; 2 volumes (Box 26)
      Penguin Classics. Introduction by Seelye. 2 versions.
    - Stories of the Old West: Tales of the Mining Camp, Calvary Troop, and Cattle Ranch, 1994; 2 volumes (Box 26)
      Norman: University of Oklahoma Press; Penguin Classics (2 versions). Edited by Seelye.
    - Tocqueville, Alexis de, undated; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Introductory essays about Tocqueville, presumably for Democracy in America.
    - Twain, Mark: The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Twain, Mark: The Adventures of Tom Sawyer, 1986; 2006; 3 volumes (Box 25)
      Penguin Classics. 1986 and 2006 editions. Introduction by Seelye.
    - Twain, Mark: Life on the Mississippi, 1990; 2009; 3 volumes (Box 26)
      World's Classics (2 versions): introduction by Seelye. Signet Classic: afterword by Seelye.
    - Twain, Mark: Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc, 1980 (Box 26)
      Stowe-Day Foundation. Introduction by Seelye.
    - Wister, Owen: The Virginian, 1988 (Box 25)
    - Wyss, Johann: The Swiss Family Robinson, 1989-1990; 3 folders (Box 11)
      Drafts, publisher's correspondence. Introduction and edited by Seelye.
    - Wyss, Johann: The Swiss Family Robinson, 1991; 2007; 2 volumes (Box 26)
      World's Classics: Introduction by Seelye. Penguin Classics: Introduction and notes by Seelye.
    - Life of Asa G. Sheldon: Wilmington Farmer, 1862 (Box 27)
      Original publication that served as the basis for Yankee Drover. Moody, printer: Woburn, Mass.
    - Yankee Drover, 1988 (Box 24)
      Introductory essay and publisher correspondence
    - Yankee Drover: Being the Unpretending Life of Asa Sheldon, Farmer, Trader, and Working Man 1788-1870, 1988 (Box 25)
      Hanover: University Press of New England, 1988. Foreword by Seelye.
- Personal, 1897-2015; undated; 5
  The Personal series contains assorted materials relevant to Seelye's life, including several versions of his curriculum vitae as well as early report cards, photographs and headshots, and school newspapers from his various schools.
  Some materials acquired with the Seelye Papers have an unknown origin. This includes the Moody Bible, which has extensive annotations but no clear connection to Seelye's work or family. There are also several folders of letters addressed to Suzanne Everett Throop, a New York book dealer in the early 1910s. Throop's correspondence arrived with the Seelye Papers labeled as "love letters," and do appear to consist largely of romantic letters from Marguarite (she also used a number of nicknames and pet names) addressed to Suzanne from 1897 and 1898. The connection to Seelye is unclear.
  - Report cards (elementary and secondary schools, Glastonbury, Connecticut), 1937-1944 (Box 24)
  - Report Card (freshman high school, Glastonbury, Connecticut), 1944-1945 (Box 29)
  - Assorted photographs, 1960s-1980s (Box 24)
    Headshots, clippings, snapshots
  - Vermont Academy/Brodine photographs, 1940s; undated (Box 24)
    Headshots and other photographs taken during Seelye's tenure at Vermont Academy
  - Vermont Academy Life issues, 1948-1949 (Box 24)
  - Vermont Academy Life issue, Summer 1960 (Box 29)
  - U.S. Navy officer service records, 1950s-1966; 2 folders (Box 24)
    Includes discharge file
  - Wesleyan Argus miscellaneous issues, 1951-1952 (Box 24)
  - Claremont College Student Life miscellaneous issues, 1956-1958 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous clippings about Seelye, 1969-2003 (Box 24)
    Includes some awards
  - Curriculum vitae files, 1958-1970; undated; 4 folders (Box 24)
    Various versions of Seelye's resumes
  - Certificate and shield, 1978 (Box 31)
  - Penguin tributes following Seelye's death, 2015 (Box 24)
  - Facebook tributes following Seelye's death, 2015 (Box 24)
  - Seelye's billfold and wallet's contents, undated (Box 24)
  - Bible belonging to Dwight L. Moody, undated (Box 24)
    Includes pencil annotations
  - Suzanne Everett Throop letters, 1897-1935; undated; 10 folders (Box 24)
    Mostly incoming correspondence intended for Suzanne Everett Throop, including a large number of love letters from "Marguerite" between 1897 and 1898 and some additional letters from "Harriet" and "Chandler" in the 1920s. It is unclear what connection these letters have to Seelye, although a notation on one of the envelopes suggests that he first opened the letters in 1977. It is possible he was using them for a writing project. These letters include family news as well as expressions of romantic love and devotion.
  - Recording of hearing, undated (Box 29, Audio-cassette RL11381-CS-003)
    Hearing regarding homeowner's association